<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="http://jaxen.org/faq.xml">

  <properties>
    <author email="bob@eng.werken.com">bob mcwhirter</author>
    <title>FAQ</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
    
    <section name="What is jaxen?">
      <p>
      The <code>jaxen</code> project is a Java XPath Engine.
      <code>jaxen</code> is a universal object model walker, capable of evaluating
      XPath expressions across multiple models.  Currently supported
      are <a href="http://dom4j.org">dom4j</a>, <a href="http://jdom.org">JDOM</a>, and DOM.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="What is the jaxen license?">
      <p>We use an Apache-style open source license which is one of the least
        restrictive licenses around, you can use <code>jaxen</code> to create new products
        without them having to be open source.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Why is jaxen useful?">
      <p>
      After implementing an XPath engine for both <a href="http://dom4j.org">dom4j</a> and
      <a href="http://jdom.org">JDOM</a>, and attempting to keep them both in sync, it was
      decided that factoring out the commonality would be a Good Thing.  Thus, <code>jaxen</code>
      provides a single point for XPath expression evaluation, regardless of the target
      object model, whether its <strong>dom4j</strong>, <strong>JDOM</strong>, <strong>DOM</strong>, 
      <strong>XOM</strong>, <strong>JavaBeans</strong>,
      or what not.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Why is jaxen better than [some other XPath technology]">
      <p>
      <code>jaxen</code> is better than <code>werken.xpath</code> specifically because it better
      handles XPath expressions, and syntax error reporting.  Additionally, since
      jaxen is a unified code-base, developer effort isn't split between maintaining
      the <strong>dom4j</strong> version and the <strong>JDOM</strong> version.  More hands working on
      the same project reduces bug count.
      </p>

      <p>
      <code>jaxen</code> may be perceived to be better than other XPath technologies since it
      provides a single cohesive API for evaluating XPaths against multiple object
      models.  Learn the <code>jaxen</code> API, and apply it to <strong>dom4j</strong>, <strong>JDOM</strong>,
      <strong>XOM</strong> or <strong>DOM</strong> trees in exactly the same way.
      </p>

      <p>
      Also, since <code>jaxen</code> works against an adaptor which provides InfoSet access
      to arbitrary object models, it should be possible to build even larger
      tools in terms of <code>jaxen</code>, to work with multiple models.  For example, an
      <strong>XQL</strong> engine could be developed, which would automagically work with
      all models already supported by <code>jaxen</code>.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="What are some related technologies?">
      <p>
      <code>jaxen</code> itself is based upon SAXPath, which is
      an event-based model for parsing XPath expressions.
      </p>

      <p>
      <code>jaxen</code> currently has navigators defined for <a href="http://dom4j.org/">dom4j</a>
      and <a href="http://jdom.org/">JDOM</a>, two popular and convenient object models
      for representing XML documents.  
      Of course, <a href="http://www.w3.org/DOM/">W3C DOM</a> is also supported.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Which version of XPath does jaxen support? Does jaxen support XPath 2?">
      <p>
      <code>jaxen</code> supports XPath 1.0. It does not support XPath 2.0. 
      XPath 2.0 is a very different spec with many things to recommend it and a
      few things not to like as well. However XPath 2.0 is not compatible with XPath 1.0.
      It is far from a simple upgrade from XPath 1.0. It has a very different data model,
      that might well require significant revisions to <code>jaxen</code>'s internal data structures,
      and possibly a very different API as well. 
      </p>
      <p>
      The current release plan focuses exclusively on XPath 1.0 compatibility. 
      Perhaps one day someone will make a branch or fork of <code>jaxen</code>
      that supports XPath 2. However, this would be a  significant undertaking,
      and so far little interest in this has been shown. 
      </p>

    </section>

    <section name="How do I support a different object model?">
      <p>
      The only thing required is an implementation of the interface 
      <code>org.jaxen.Navigator</code>.  Not all of the interface is required,
      and a default implementation, in the form of <code>org.jaxen.DefaultNavigator</code>
      is also provided.
      </p>

      <p>
      Since many of the XPath axes can be defined in terms of each other (for example,
      the <code>ancestor</code> axis is merely a the <code>parent</code> recursively
      applied), only a few low-level axis iterators are required to initially get
      started.  Of course, you may implement them directly, instead of relying upon
      <code>jaxen</code>'s composition ability.
      </p>

    </section>

    <section name="Is jaxen only good for XPath evaluation?">
      <p>
      No. 
      </p>

      <p>
      The <code>DocumentNavigators</code> provided with <code>jaxen</code> would be used
      by themselves, without the XPath evaluation engine, to provide univeral
      access to many object models for other technologies.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Who uses jaxen?">
      <p>
      <code>jaxen</code> has been embedded directly into <strong>dom4j</strong> and 
      <strong><a href="http://www.xom.nu/">XOM 1.1</a></strong> to provide
      easy XPath evaluation directly from your documents.  Additionally, it's
      being integrated into David Megginson's 
      <a href="http://newsml-toolkit.sourceforge.net/">NewsML Framework</a>.
      Tom Copeland's <a href="http://pmd.sourceforge.net/">PMD</a> static code analyzer uses jaxen to query Java code structures using XPath.  
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="How do I write a query for namespace qualified elements/attributes in Jaxen?">
      <p>
      The XPath expression that selects elements or attributes in a namespace 
      looks exactly the same as it does in any other XPath context; that is, use prefixed names where the
      prefixes are bound to the namespace URIs. For example,
      </p>
      
      <p><code>/pre:bar/@xlink:href</code></p>
      
      <p>
      However, because a Java program is not an XML document, it is also necessary to
      bind the prefixes to the appropriate namespace URIs through a <code>NamespaceContext</code> object.
      For example, this code sets up and then executes the above query:
      </p>
      
      <pre>  XPath xpath = new DOMXPath("/foo:bar/@xlink:href", nav);
  SimpleNamespaceContext nsContext = new SimpleNamespaceContext();
  nsContext.addNamespace("pre", "http://www.foo.org/");
  nsContext.addNamespace("xlink", "http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink");
  xpath.setNamespaceContext(nsContext);
  List result = contextpath.selectNodes(document);</pre>
        
        <p>
        As a shortcut, you can simply add a namespace binding
        to the XPath expression's current context using the 
        <code>addNamespace</code> method: 
        </p>
        
        <pre>  XPath xpath = new DOMXPath("/pre:root");
  xpath.addNamespace("pre", "http://www.example.org/");
  List result = xpath.selectNodes(root);</pre>
        
        
       <p>
         If the namespace context does not contain a binding for a prefix that is used in
         the XPath expression, an <code>UnresolvableException</code> 
         (a subclass of <code>JaxenException</code>
         is thrown when you attempt
         to evaluate it.
       </p>
      
    </section>

    <section name="How do I write a query for namespace qualified elements/attributes in the default namespace?">
      <p>
      The same way you do for elements and attributes that
      are in prefixed namespaces. That is, you use a prefix in the XPath expression and bind 
      the prefix to the namespace URI. You do this even if the document you're querying
      uses unprefixed namespaced qualified names. In XPath 1.0, all unprefixed names are unqualified. 
      There is no requirement that the prefixes used in the XPath expression are the same as the prefixes used in the
      document being queried. Only the namespace URIs need to match, not the prefixes. 
      </p>
      
      <p>For example, this code fragment queries the document 
      <code><![CDATA[[<root xmlns="http://www.example.org/"/>]]></code> using the XPath expression
      <code>/pre:root</code>:
      
      </p>
      
      <pre>        Element root = doc.createElementNS("http://www.example.org/", "root");
        doc.appendChild(root);
        XPath xpath = new DOMXPath("/pre:root");
        SimpleNamespaceContext context = new SimpleNamespaceContext();
        context.addNamespace("pre", "http://www.example.org/");
        xpath.setNamespaceContext(context);
        List result = xpath.selectNodes(root);</pre>

     <p>Alternately, using the shortcut:
      </p>
      
      <pre>        Element root = doc.createElementNS("http://www.example.org/", "root");
        doc.appendChild(root);
        XPath xpath = new DOMXPath("/pre:root");
        xpath.addNamespace("pre", "http://www.example.org/");
        List result = xpath.selectNodes(root);</pre>

      
    </section>

  </body>
</document>









