<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://jaxen.org/faq.xml">
  <body>
    <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
    
    <section title="What is Jaxen?">
      <p>
      The <i>Jaxen</i> project is a Java XPath Engine.
      Jaxen is a universal object model walker, capable of evaluating
      XPath expressions across multiple models.  Currently supported
      are <a href="http://dom4j.org">dom4j</a> and <a href="http://jdom.org">JDOM</a>.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section title="What is the Jaxen license?">
      <p>We use an Apache-style open source license which is one of the least
        restrictive licenses around, you can use <i>Jaxen</i> to create new products
        without them having to be open source.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section title="Why is Jaxen useful?">
      <p>
      After implementing an XPath engine for both <a href="http://dom4j.org">dom4j</a> and
      <a href="http://jdom.org">JDOM</a>, and attempting to keep them both in sync, it was
      decided that factoring out the commonality would be a Good Thing.  Thus, Jaxen
      provides a single point for XPath expression evaluation, regardless of the target
      object model, whether its <b>dom4j</b>, <b>JDOM</b>, <b>DOM</b>, <b>JavaBeans</b>,
      or whatnot.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section title="What are some related technologies?">
      <p>
      Jaxen itself is based upon <a href="http://saxpath.org/">SAXPath</a>, which is
      an event-based model for parsing XPath expressions.
      </p>

      <p>
      Jaxen currently has navigators defined for <a href="http://dom4j.org/">dom4j</a>
      and <a href="http://jdom.org/">JDOM</a>, two popular and convenient object models
      for representing XML documents.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section title="How do I support a different object model?">
      <p>
      The only thing required is an implementation of the interface 
      <code>org.jaxen.Navigator</code>.  Not all of the interface is required,
      and a default implementation, in the form of <code>org.jaxen.DefaultNavigator</code>
      is also provided.
      </p>

      <p>
      Since many of the XPath axes can be defined in terms of each other (for example,
      the <code>ancestor</code> axis is merely a the <code>parent</code> recursively
      applied), only a few low-level axis iterators are required to initially get
      started.  Of course, you may implement them directly, instead of relying upon
      Jaxen's composition ability.
      </p>

      <p>
      To support a model such as W3C-DOM, it should be relatively easy to start with
      an existing <code>Navigator</code> (such as <code>dom4j</code>'s), and quickly
      get up to speed.
      </p>

    </section>

  </body>
</document>









