<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="bob.mcwhirter@redhat.com">bob mcwhirter</author>
    <title>Releases</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Official Builds">

<p>
The current version is 2.0.5. This release is completely API compatible with version 2.0.0.
</p>

      
      <ul>
        <li><a href="https://github.com/jaxen-xpath/jaxen/releases/download/v2.0.5/jaxen-2.0.5-bin.zip">2.0.5 binaries in zip format.</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://github.com/jaxen-xpath/jaxen/releases/download/v2.0.5/jaxen-2.0.5-bin.tar.gz">2.0.5 binaries in tar.gz format.</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://github.com/jaxen-xpath/jaxen/releases/download/v2.0.5/jaxen-2.0.5-bin.tar.bz2">2.0.5 binaries in bz2 format.</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://github.com/jaxen-xpath/jaxen/releases/download/v2.0.5/jaxen-2.0.5-src.zip">2.0.5 sources in zip format.</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://github.com/jaxen-xpath/jaxen/releases/download/v2.0.5/jaxen-2.0.5-src.tar.gz">2.0.5 sources in tar.gz format.</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://github.com/jaxen-xpath/jaxen/releases/download/v2.0.5/jaxen-2.0.5-src.tar.bz2">2.0.5 sources in tar.bz2 format.</a></li>
      </ul>


 <p>Version 2.0.6 fixes one bug in the new iterative algorithms that incorrectly evaluated some parenthesized XPath expressions like ((//A)[2]//B)[1]/C.</p>

 <p>Version 2.0.5 replaced still more recursive algorithms from the 
 core parser. This enables Jaxen to handle even larger and more complex XPath expressions.
 For the recursive code that remains, higher level evaluation and parsing now catches stack overflow
 errors if they do occur, and wraps them inside a regular checked <code>JaxenException</code>
 so it won't bring down the entire program. This should be fairly robust and complete
 protection against DoS attacks on recursive code, even with arbitrary untrusted input.
 </p>
      
<p>
Version 2.0.4 fixed a bug in XPath parser precedence so expressions that combine the union
operator with additive expressions are now evaluated correctly. It also deprecated the simplify
method and replaced recursive algorithms to enable Jaxen to handle longer and more
complex queries while preventing one class of denial-of-service attacks.
</p>

<p>
Version 2.0.3 fixed two bugs in XPath evaluation: one involving the use of decimal numbers in predicates
and one deduplicating nodes in the uncommon case where duplicate IDs appeared within the argument to the <code>id()</code> function.
It also stopped publishing the integration tests subproject (jaxen:jaxen-integration) to Maven Central.
</p>

      
<p>
Version 2.0.2 fixed two bugs in XPath evaluation: one involving proper handling of NaN and Inf 
values in the <code>substring</code> function and one correctly ordering
attribute nodes before child nodes in union operations. 
</p>


<p>
Version 2.0.1 fixed several bugs in XPath evaluation.
It also made builds automated, immutable, and reproducible
to resist supply chain and MITM attacks.
</p>
   
<p>
2.0.0 now requires Java 1.5 or later, 
and marks the third party models for XOM, JDOM, and dom4j optional
so dependency trees should be much smaller.
Although this is a major release, it's almost completely API compatible and should be a drop-in
replacement for most existing projects. 
</p>

<p>
 1.2.0 required Java 1.4 or later, and stopped bundling the org.w3c.dom classes.
It also deprecated the <code>org.jaxen.pattern</code> package.
It should be fully compatible with code written to Jaxen 1.1.
</p>

<p>
 1.1.6 fixed several bugs in IEEE 754 arithmetic. 
</p>

<p>
1.1 is a major upgrade that significantly improved jaxen's conformance to the underlying XPath 1.0 specification. 
This release
is a vast improvement over 1.0, and all users are strongly encouraged to upgrade. 
With a few small exceptions (e.g. the <code>document()</code> function moved to the 
<code>org.jaxen.function.xslt</code> package, the <code>IdentityHashMap</code> class was deleted,
and the ElectricXML navigator was deleted) 1.1
is backwards compatible with code written to the 1.0 APIs.
      </p>

    </section>


  </body>

</document>
